<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Blunder Valley</title>
  <subtitle>Something doesn&#39;t add up about the Wonder Valley data centre project.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/" />
  <updated>2025-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://blundervalley.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mr. Roboto</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Your pension, up in smoke?</title>
    <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/blog/pension-funds/" />
    <updated>2025-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://blundervalley.ca/blog/pension-funds/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;from-ottawa-to-edmonton-politicians-and-bankers-agree-on-one-thing-funneling-your-retirement-savings-into-risky-ai-gambles&quot;&gt;From Ottawa to Edmonton, politicians and bankers agree on one thing: funneling your retirement savings into risky AI gambles.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently there have been a few changes, and proposed changes, to the rules for how pension funds can invest your retirement savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And whether we&#39;re talking about Freeland &amp;amp; Carney in Ottawa, or Smith &amp;amp; Harper in Alberta, one of the goals of those rule changes seems to be to get the managers of Canada&#39;s public pension funds (who are supposed to have independence from government interference) to invest your retirement money into AI and data centres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a lot of hype around AI. But a lot of people are warning that AI is another tech investment bubble. So, why are these politicians so eager to fund these projects with your savings?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pension-funds-got-burned-by-the-crypto-bubble-of-2021&quot;&gt;Pension funds got burned by the crypto bubble of 2021&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin O&#39;Leary has been trying to find ways to crack open people&#39;s nest eggs for a while. In 2022, when he was hauled in front of the US Senate to answer questions about the collapse of cryptocurrency exchange FTX, he said that &amp;quot;the potential of crypto is for it to be indexed with sovereign wealth and pension, where about 70% of the world&#39;s wealth is actually managed.&amp;quot; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/WwTuSzjycIg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;YouTube video&lt;/a&gt;, timestamp = 14:15)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the two years since then, cryptocurrency prices have rebounded. But assets with wild, unpredictable swings (and in the case of crypto, with no underlying value) don&#39;t tend to be very attractive to pension funds looking for stable long-term returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the midst of the crypto craze of 2021, though, when everybody seemed convinced that the cryptocurrency market was for real, that use cases were going to be found any day now, and widespread adoption was just around the corner, some pension funds &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; take the bait:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CDPQ ended up losing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/67048159-82aa-4e96-bfb3-f1764f632375&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;$150 million on a fraudulent crypto lending scheme called Celsius&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Ontario Teachers&#39; Pension Plan (OTPP) lost all US$95 million of their investment in FTX&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;guess-who-was-hyping-up-ftx-and-crypto&quot;&gt;Guess who was hyping up FTX and crypto?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems noteworthy that the OTPP made their investment just three months after &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/ftx-and-kevin-oleary-announce-long-term-investment-and-spokesperson-relationship-301352189.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kevin O&#39;Leary had become a spokesperson&lt;/a&gt; for FTX, which means they invested at a time when O&#39;Leary was singing the praises of CEO Sam Bankman-Fried, now a convicted fraudster serving a 25-year prison sentence for stealing billions in customer funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile the CEO of Celsius, Alex Mashinsky, is serving 30 years for fraud and market manipulation. CDPQ chief executive Charles Emond, speaking during the first few days after Celsius declared bankruptcy, put it mildly, saying: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/67048159-82aa-4e96-bfb3-f1764f632375&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;in these disruptive technologies, there&#39;s ups and downs.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-push-in-ottawa-to-change-pension-fund-rules&quot;&gt;A push in Ottawa to change pension fund rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2023, Evan Siddall wrote an op-ed in the Globe and Mail: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/commentary/article-federal-government-should-not-be-pushing-pension-funds-to-invest-more/&quot;&gt;Federal government should not be pushing pension funds to invest more in Canada&lt;/a&gt;. At that time, Siddall was the CEO of Alberta Investment Management Corp. (AIMCo), which manages the pension funds of public sector employees in Alberta including teachers, police, firefighters, and municipal workers. He argued that the federal government shouldn&#39;t be using people&#39;s retirement savings to compensate for their lack of investment in Canadian economic development, and was worried that the Fall Economic Statement of 2023 was opening the door to doing exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But business executives, whose salaries and bonuses are often connected to their companies&#39; stock prices, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-pension-funds-investing-campaign/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;continued pressuring&lt;/a&gt; the federal government to put their thumb on the scale. And by April 2024, then-finance minister Chrystia Freeland had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-stephen-poloz-will-lead-push-to-boost-domestic-investment-by-canadian/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hired former Bank of Canada governor Stephen Poloz&lt;/a&gt; to find ways to coax pension funds into investing more in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By September, Brookfield Asset Management was making their pitch to Chrystia Freeland for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://financialpost.com/fp-finance/brookfield-ottawa-major-pensions-being-discussed&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;$50 billion investment fund&lt;/a&gt; that would be made up of money from pension funds and the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this didn&#39;t go over very well, partly because the pension funds didn&#39;t like the idea, but also because Brookfield&#39;s chair is Mark Carney, another former BoC governor who was &lt;em&gt;also working as an advisor&lt;/em&gt; to the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, Poloz continued to work on crafting policy. One proposal was a program where the government would contribute up to $15 billion toward a $45 billion AI data centre investment fund (where pension funds could contribute up to $30 billion, and the feds would partially match the investment, adding $1 of public money for every $2 of pension money invested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the original policy proposal included a requirement that data centres must be powered by renewables - but by the time the 2024 Fall Economic Statement was released in December, this requirement &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-freeland-confirms-ottawa-to-develop-15-billion-program-to-help-pension/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;had vanished&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-pension-fund-takeover-in-edmonton&quot;&gt;A pension fund takeover in Edmonton&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in November, Premier Danielle Smith&#39;s government suddenly &lt;a href=&quot;https://nationalpost.com/news/alberta-government-wants-stephen-harper-aimco-chairman/wcm/c317ae57-7969-43fa-9427-acf56b540f48&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;fired&lt;/a&gt; the entire AIMCo board along with 4 top executives, including CEO Evan Siddall, who had written that op-ed criticizing the federal government&#39;s attempt to influence pension funds&#39; investments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than two weeks later, Stephen Harper was announced as the new chair of AIMCo&#39;s board. This appointment immediately led to widespread worry (including from senior fellows at the staunchly conservative &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/commentary/article-albertas-aimco-shakeup-could-mean-government-control-of-pension-fund/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fraser Institute&lt;/a&gt;) that the Alberta government was seeking to politicize AIMCo, which manages $169 billion in assets, most of which is workers&#39; retirement savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as evidence that politicization was the goal, Premier Smith had reportedly been hoping to appoint Harper to the role &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nationalpost.com/news/alberta-government-wants-stephen-harper-aimco-chairman/wcm/c317ae57-7969-43fa-9427-acf56b540f48&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;for some time&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;, which makes it pretty clear that AIMCo&#39;s board was fired not due to mismanagement, but as a way for the province to seize control over the fund&#39;s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kevin-o-leary-shoots-his-shot&quot;&gt;Kevin O&#39;Leary shoots his shot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter Kevin O&#39;Leary, with the perfect plan to snatch up Canadians&#39; pension money not only from the proposed federal AI data centre fund, but also from a newly politicized AIMCo, eager to invest in the expansion of fossil fuel infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Premier Smith was &lt;a href=&quot;https://mdgreenview.ab.ca/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/GIG-O-Leary-Release_2024.12.09-FINAL.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;immediately on board&lt;/a&gt; with O&#39;Leary&#39;s proposal, declaring, &amp;quot;this is fantastic news for Alberta. Our efforts to attract investment, grow our technology and innovation sector, and leverage our natural and human resources are being noticed. I’m excited to watch this project unfold in the months and years to come.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even putting aside the issues around pension funds, is this really &amp;quot;fantastic news for Alberta&amp;quot;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-ai-a-risky-investment&quot;&gt;Is AI a risky investment?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most truthful answer is, &amp;quot;it depends&amp;quot;. There are definitely useful applications for some of the technologies that fall under the umbrella of things we lump together as &#39;AI&#39;. Machine learning, for example, has been quietly useful for decades, and is comparatively inexpensive to run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there&#39;s Generative AI (e.g. ChatGPT, Gemini, Copilot, Midjourney, Stable Diffusion). Companies that make GenAI systems are losing a massive amount of money every year; one of them, OpenAI, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2024/09/27/openai-sees-5-billion-loss-this-year-on-3point7-billion-in-revenue.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lost $5 billion in 2024&lt;/a&gt;. These systems require so much hardware and resources to run that they &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theregister.com/2025/01/06/altman_gpt_profits/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;aren&#39;t able to charge their customers enough&lt;/a&gt; to cover their costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Ah,&amp;quot; the AI companies say, &amp;quot;but soon these systems will be far more useful, and won&#39;t go telling users to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/24141648/ai-ebook-grift-mushroom-foraging-mycological-society&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;eat deadly mushrooms&lt;/a&gt;, drink &lt;a href=&quot;https://gizmodo.com/paknsave-ai-savey-recipe-bot-chlorine-gas-1850725057&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;aromatic water&amp;quot; (aka mustard gas, a chemical weapon)&lt;/a&gt; or put &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cd11gzejgz4o&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glue on pizza&lt;/a&gt; to keep the toppings from sliding off. We just need more money to build bigger data centres, and ten times as much data to train our models on!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with that: they&#39;ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://theweek.com/tech/ai-running-out-of-data&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;already scraped&lt;/a&gt; pretty much the entirety of the internet. Which means that no matter how much more money gets thrown at these Generative AI systems, they&#39;re unlikely to get much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more people have been sounding the alarm, warning investors that the AI market is a speculative bubble. Here&#39;s a few of the headlines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bnnbloomberg.ca/business/technology/2024/07/18/goldmans-top-stock-analyst-is-waiting-for-ai-bubble-to-burst/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Goldman’s Top Stock Analyst Is Waiting for AI Bubble to Burst&lt;/a&gt; (Bloomberg)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/story/money/investing/2024/12/23/artificial-intelligence-bubble-burst-2025/77081750007/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Will the artificial intelligence bubble burst in 2025? Here are 4 reasons it might.&lt;/a&gt; (USA Today)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.barrons.com/amp/articles/broadcom-stock-price-ai-chips-d4866d4b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Broadcom Stock Drops as Chip Stocks Slide. Is the AI Trade Ending?&lt;/a&gt; (Barron&#39;s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theregister.com/2025/01/06/altman_gpt_profits/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Even at $200/mo, Altman admits ChatGPT Pro struggles to turn a profit&lt;/a&gt; (The Register)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techtarget.com/searchenterpriseai/news/366599640/Enterprises-struggle-to-find-business-value-with-GenAI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Enterprises struggle to find business value with GenAI&lt;/a&gt; (TechTarget)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2025/01/07/howard-marks-sees-cautionary-signs-of-bubble-says-investors-shouldnt-ignore-todays-high-valuation.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Howard Marks sees cautionary signs of a bubble&lt;/a&gt; (CNBC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up: AI data centres are an incredibly risky investment at this stage. Be wary of any politician or entrepreneur trying to steer your retirement money (or our public funds) into these schemes. Over the last quarter-century, we&#39;ve seen enough tech hype cycles (dot-com, crypto, NFTs, the metaverse, VR, just to name a few) to know how this story ends. Which raises a question: are these politicians and business leaders just suckers falling for the hype of the day? Or are they hoping to prop up the market with our retirement savings, so their pals can cash out before the bubble bursts?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Water Consumption Question</title>
    <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/blog/water-consumption/" />
    <updated>2025-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://blundervalley.ca/blog/water-consumption/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-water-will-this-project-consume-exactly&quot;&gt;How much water will this project consume, exactly?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-quick-look-at-the-numbers&quot;&gt;A quick look at the numbers:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data centres can consume (evaporate) between 1 and 9 litres of water per kWh used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even assuming only 1L/kWh, a 7.5 GW data centre will consume 65.7 million cubic metres of water per year (65.7 billion L/year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gas plants consume about 2L water for every 1kWh produced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at this rate, 7.5GW gas plant generation consumes 131.4 million cubic metres of water per year (131.4 billion L/year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carbon Capture &amp;amp; Storage (CCS), if implemented, can increase this figure to between 2.6L/kWh and 3.36L/kWh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This means an additional 40 to 90 million cubic metres of water consumed per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All told, this project could consume on the order of 280 billion litres of water per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&#39;s important to note that these figures are not based on information from the project itself. That&#39;s because at present, almost no information has been made public. O&#39;Leary Ventures and the Greenview Industrial Gateway must immediately make details available about the exact technologies they plan to deploy, so that the public can properly assess the project&#39;s likely impact on the surrounding communities and natural environment. A request for this information was emailed to GIG Executive Director Kyle Reiling on 2024-01-04, and if there is a response, it will be noted here.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-centres&quot;&gt;Data Centres&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data centres use a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of water. Figures vary, and some tech companies have a habit of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.is/lBf5H&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cooking the books&lt;/a&gt; when it comes to documenting their resource consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One number we have is from Meta: they &lt;a href=&quot;https://dgtlinfra.com/data-center-water-usage/#Water_Usage_Effectiveness_WUE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;estimate&lt;/a&gt; that the industry average is 1.8L of water consumed (evaporated) for every 1kWh of electricity used by a data centre. Other &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2304.03271&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; gives a range of between 1L and 9L consumed per kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, outside temperatures play a big role in determining the amount of water consumed, and it&#39;s true that the cooler climate in Northern Alberta is an advantage here for much of the year. But when we&#39;re talking about a 7.5GW project, even that low-end estimate of 1L/kWh represents an enormous amount of water: over the course of a year, this works out to &lt;strong&gt;65.7 million cubic metres of water&lt;/strong&gt;, a figure that is already more than 2x the &lt;a href=&quot;https://greenviewindustrial.ca/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Water2-1200x681.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;24 million cubic metres&lt;/a&gt; that the Greenview Industrial Gateway (GIG) has asked for permission to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we haven&#39;t even gotten to the water use of gas plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;gas-plants&quot;&gt;Gas Plants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The water consumption of a typical &#39;wet-cooled&#39; gas plant is roughly &lt;a href=&quot;https://sequestration.mit.edu/pdf/2012_AD_HJH_WorkingPaper-WaterUse_at_PowerPlants.pdf&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;2L per kWh generated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also &#39;dry-cooled&#39; gas plants that use almost no water for cooling. However, given that the GIG&#39;s executive director Kyle Reiling said in an interview that when it comes to this project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/yVKxjAQyMTg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;the large majority of the water is for the electrical production&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, it&#39;s a safe assumption that these proposed gas plants are the kind that use a ton of water. At 7.5 GW total, and a rate of 2L per kWh, power generation would require a staggering &lt;strong&gt;131.4 billion litres&lt;/strong&gt; of water each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-wait-theres-more&quot;&gt;But wait, there&#39;s more&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because gas plants represent a massive amount of carbon emissions compared to energy generation from renewables like wind and solar, advocates of burning fossil fuels like to talk about Carbon Capture and Storage (CCS) as a way to lower the carbon footprint of projects like this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not only does CCS &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.mit.edu/ask-mit/if-fossil-fuel-power-plant-uses-carbon-capture-and-storage-what-percent-energy-it-makes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;increase the cost&lt;/a&gt; of energy generation at a time when wind and solar are already the less expensive options, it also increases a gas plant&#39;s water consumption significantly. Depending on the exact process, this increase is likely between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1876610217319720&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;31% and 68%&lt;/a&gt;. This means that, if O&#39;Leary and the GIG are planning on capturing carbon emissions, these gas plants would consume between &lt;strong&gt;171 billion and 220 billion litres of water per year - around 7 to 10 times the amount of water they&#39;ve asked for permission to use&lt;/strong&gt;. Add this to the earlier estimate of water consumption by the data centres themselves, and the total could well reach &lt;strong&gt;280 billion litres per year&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>So Many Unanswered Questions</title>
    <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/blog/so-many-unanswered-questions/" />
    <updated>2024-12-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://blundervalley.ca/blog/so-many-unanswered-questions/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/edmonton/why-celebrity-investor-kevin-o-leary-is-proposing-a-massive-ai-data-centre-in-northern-alberta-1.7407506&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;statement to the media&lt;/a&gt; about the Wonder Valley project, Kevin O&#39;Leary said that &amp;quot;people should be very skeptical and they should just watch, because we&#39;ll be very transparent as we develop this.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as of December 26, 2024, the public has virtually no answers to the huge number of questions surrounding this proposed project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;water&quot;&gt;Water&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much water will this project consume?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will the water use affect communities and farmers in the region?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To what extent will this project worsen drought conditions in the region and/or increase wildfire risk?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the unevaporated portion of water drawn be sufficiently cooled and free of industrial contaminants before being dumped back into the local environment? How will this be ensured?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://blundervalley.ca/blog/water-consumption/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; about the extraordinary amount of water consumed by data centres and gas plants)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;cost-to-the-public&quot;&gt;Cost to the Public&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What subsidies, grants, or loans will this project be asking different levels of government for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will this project be seeking investment capital from any pension funds or sovereign wealth funds?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how much public money will be spent to provide needed infrastructure for this project (e.g. road upgrades, new water treatment facilities, etc)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://blundervalley.ca/blog/pension-funds/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; about how both the federal Liberals &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; Alberta&#39;s UCP seem to like this AI data centre proposal)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;jobs&quot;&gt;Jobs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most jobs associated with data centre projects are short term for the construction phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many of the &amp;quot;thousands of jobs&amp;quot; that will supposedly be created are only temporary, and how many are permanent positions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the Wonder Valley website, the image showing the &#39;Development Concept Plan&#39; includes a large area labeled &#39;Worker Camp&#39;. Does this mean that most workers will be temporary employees, and hired from outside the local area?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;noise&quot;&gt;Noise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noise from data centres has led to &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/6982015/bitcoin-mining-texas-health/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;severe health problems&lt;/a&gt; for residents (including people, pets and livestock) in surrounding areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will noise be mitigated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much noise will this project produce?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;finances&quot;&gt;Finances&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI companies are &lt;a href=&quot;https://futurism.com/the-byte/microsoft-losing-money-ai&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;losing billions of dollars&lt;/a&gt; every year. Financial analysts are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goldmansachs.com/images/migrated/insights/pages/gs-research/gen-ai--too-much-spend%2C-too-little-benefit-/TOM_AI%202.0_ForRedaction.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;increasingly worried&lt;/a&gt; that AI stock valuations are a bubble. So:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens to this project if the AI market crashes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whose investments will be prioritized in the event this project goes bankrupt?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;carbon-emissions&quot;&gt;Carbon emissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much CO2 will this project be responsible for emitting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will this project mean that Canadians end up paying higher carbon taxes, as a method of reducing emissions elsewhere?&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbon Capture and Storage is &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.mit.edu/ask-mit/if-fossil-fuel-power-plant-uses-carbon-capture-and-storage-what-percent-energy-it-makes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;expensive and difficult to implement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What percentage of carbon emissions will be captured and stored?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will those emissions be captured and stored?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;energy-grid&quot;&gt;Energy Grid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will this project need to use any electricity from Alberta&#39;s grid?
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;have-more-questions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have more questions?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a question about the Wonder Valley project, feel free to get in touch, and I&#39;ll add it to the list! You can send your questions to:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;welcometoblundervalley &lt;em&gt;at&lt;/em&gt; protonmail &lt;em&gt;dot&lt;/em&gt; com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>