<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>BlunderValley.ca</title>
  <subtitle>Something doesn&#39;t add up about the Wonder Valley data centre project.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/" />
  <updated>2025-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://blundervalley.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mr. Roboto</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The Water Consumption Question</title>
    <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/blog/water-consumption/" />
    <updated>2025-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://blundervalley.ca/blog/water-consumption/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-water-will-this-project-consume-exactly&quot;&gt;How much water will this project consume, exactly?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-quick-look-at-the-numbers&quot;&gt;A quick look at the numbers:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data centres can consume (evaporate) between 1 and 9 litres of water per kWh used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even assuming only 1L/kWh, a 7.5 GW data centre will consume 65.7 million cubic metres of water per year (65.7 billion L/year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gas plants consume about 2L water for every 1kWh produced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at this rate, 7.5GW gas plant generation consumes 131.4 million cubic metres of water per year (131.4 billion L/year)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carbon Capture &amp;amp; Storage (CCS), if implemented, can increase this figure to between 2.6L/kWh and 3.36L/kWh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This means an additional 40 to 90 million cubic metres of water consumed per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All told, this project could consume on the order of 280 billion litres of water per year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&#39;s important to note that these figures are not based on information from the project itself. That&#39;s because at present, almost no information has been made public. O&#39;Leary Ventures and the Greenview Industrial Gateway must immediately make details available about the exact technologies they plan to deploy, so that the public can properly assess the project&#39;s likely impact on the surrounding communities and natural environment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-centres&quot;&gt;Data Centres&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data centres use a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of water. Figures vary, and some tech companies have a habit of &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.is/lBf5H&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cooking the books&lt;/a&gt; when it comes to documenting their resource consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One number we have is from Meta: they &lt;a href=&quot;https://dgtlinfra.com/data-center-water-usage/#Water_Usage_Effectiveness_WUE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;estimate&lt;/a&gt; that the industry average is 1.8L of water consumed (evaporated) for every 1kWh of electricity used by a data centre. Other &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2304.03271&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; gives a range of between 1L and 9L consumed per kWh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, outside temperatures play a big role in determining the amount of water consumed, and it&#39;s true that the cooler climate in Northern Alberta is an advantage here for much of the year. But when we&#39;re talking about a 7.5GW project, even that low-end estimate of 1L/kWh represents an enormous amount of water: over the course of a year, this works out to &lt;strong&gt;65.7 million cubic metres of water&lt;/strong&gt;, a figure that is already more than 2x the &lt;a href=&quot;https://greenviewindustrial.ca/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Water2-1200x681.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;24 million cubic metres&lt;/a&gt; that the Greenview Industrial Gateway (GIG) has asked for permission to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we haven&#39;t even gotten to the water use of gas plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;gas-plants&quot;&gt;Gas Plants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The water consumption of a typical &#39;wet-cooled&#39; gas plant is roughly &lt;a href=&quot;https://sequestration.mit.edu/pdf/2012_AD_HJH_WorkingPaper-WaterUse_at_PowerPlants.pdf&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;2L per kWh generated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also &#39;dry-cooled&#39; gas plants that use almost no water for cooling. However, given that the GIG&#39;s executive director Kyle Reiling said in an interview that when it comes to this project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/yVKxjAQyMTg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;the large majority of the water is for the electrical production&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, it&#39;s a safe assumption that these proposed gas plants are the kind that use a ton of water. At 7.5 GW total, and a rate of 2L per kWh, power generation would require a staggering &lt;strong&gt;131.4 billion litres&lt;/strong&gt; of water each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-wait-theres-more&quot;&gt;But wait, there&#39;s more&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because gas plants represent a massive amount of carbon emissions compared to energy generation from renewables like wind and solar, advocates of burning fossil fuels like to talk about Carbon Capture and Storage (CCS) as a way to lower the carbon footprint of projects like this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not only does CCS &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.mit.edu/ask-mit/if-fossil-fuel-power-plant-uses-carbon-capture-and-storage-what-percent-energy-it-makes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;increase the cost&lt;/a&gt; of energy generation at a time when wind and solar are already the less expensive options, it also increases a gas plant&#39;s water consumption significantly. Depending on the exact process, this increase is likely between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1876610217319720&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;31% and 68%&lt;/a&gt;. This means that, if O&#39;Leary and the GIG are planning on capturing carbon emissions, these gas plants would consume between &lt;strong&gt;171 billion and 220 billion litres of water per year - around 7 to 10 times the amount of water they&#39;ve asked for permission to use&lt;/strong&gt;. Add this to the earlier estimate of water consumption by the data centres themselves, and the total could well reach &lt;strong&gt;280 billion litres per year&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>So Many Unanswered Questions</title>
    <link href="https://blundervalley.ca/blog/so-many-unanswered-questions/" />
    <updated>2024-12-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://blundervalley.ca/blog/so-many-unanswered-questions/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/edmonton/why-celebrity-investor-kevin-o-leary-is-proposing-a-massive-ai-data-centre-in-northern-alberta-1.7407506&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;statement to the media&lt;/a&gt; about the Wonder Valley project, Kevin O&#39;Leary said that &amp;quot;people should be very skeptical and they should just watch, because we&#39;ll be very transparent as we develop this.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as of December 26, 2024, the public has virtually no answers to the huge number of questions surrounding this proposed project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;water&quot;&gt;Water&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much water will this project consume?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will the water use affect communities and farmers in the region?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To what extent will this project worsen drought conditions in the region and/or increase wildfire risk?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the unevaporated portion of water drawn be sufficiently cooled and free of industrial contaminants before being dumped back into the local environment? How will this be ensured?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(see also &lt;a href=&quot;https://blundervalley.ca/blog/water-consumption/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; about the extraordinary amount of water consumed by data centres and gas plants)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;cost-to-the-public&quot;&gt;Cost to the Public&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What subsidies, grants, or loans will this project be asking different levels of government for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will this project be seeking investment capital from any pension funds or sovereign wealth funds?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how much public money will be spent to provide needed infrastructure for this project (e.g. road upgrades, new water treatment facilities, etc)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;jobs&quot;&gt;Jobs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most jobs associated with data centre projects are short term for the construction phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many of the &amp;quot;thousands of jobs&amp;quot; that will supposedly be created are only temporary, and how many are permanent positions?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the Wonder Valley website, the image showing the &#39;Development Concept Plan&#39; includes a large area labeled &#39;Worker Camp&#39;. Does this mean that most workers will be temporary employees, and hired from outside the local area?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;noise&quot;&gt;Noise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noise from data centres has led to &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/6982015/bitcoin-mining-texas-health/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;severe health problems&lt;/a&gt; for residents (including people, pets and livestock) in surrounding areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will noise be mitigated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much noise will this project produce?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;finances&quot;&gt;Finances&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI companies are &lt;a href=&quot;https://futurism.com/the-byte/microsoft-losing-money-ai&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;losing billions of dollars&lt;/a&gt; every year. Financial analysts are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goldmansachs.com/images/migrated/insights/pages/gs-research/gen-ai--too-much-spend%2C-too-little-benefit-/TOM_AI%202.0_ForRedaction.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;increasingly worried&lt;/a&gt; that AI stock valuations are a bubble. So:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens to this project if the AI market crashes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whose investments will be prioritized in the event this project goes bankrupt?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;carbon-emissions&quot;&gt;Carbon emissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much CO2 will this project be responsible for emitting?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will this project mean that Canadians end up paying higher carbon taxes, as a method of reducing emissions elsewhere?&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbon Capture and Storage is &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.mit.edu/ask-mit/if-fossil-fuel-power-plant-uses-carbon-capture-and-storage-what-percent-energy-it-makes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;expensive and difficult to implement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What percentage of carbon emissions will be captured and stored?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will those emissions be captured and stored?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;energy-grid&quot;&gt;Energy Grid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will this project need to use any electricity from Alberta&#39;s grid?
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;have-more-questions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Have more questions?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a question about the Wonder Valley project, feel free to get in touch, and I&#39;ll add it to the list! You can send your questions to:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;welcometoblundervalley &lt;em&gt;at&lt;/em&gt; protonmail &lt;em&gt;dot&lt;/em&gt; com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>